Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是斯科特-曼利
Thanks to 20 years of continuous occupation of space
由于20年来对太空的持续占领
we have a wealth of photographs and videos from low earth orbit.
我们拥有大量来自低地球轨道的照片和视频
And they are wonderful things to watch.
它们是值得观看的美妙事物
Sometimes they show amazing things like this Soyuz launching towards the ISS
有时 它们展示了令人惊奇的事情 比如这个联盟号向国际空间站发射的照片
but even the random everyday views from low earth orbit are compelling and hypnotic.
但即使是来自低地球轨道的随机的日常景观也是令人信服和催眠的
They show the world moving slowly below the observer, land and sea.
它们显示了世界在观察者下方缓慢移动 陆地和海洋
Sometimes cities and of course clouds hanging in the atmosphere.
有时还有城市 当然还有悬挂在大气层中的云彩
Looking to the edge of the globe you can see the thin atmosphere extending up towards space.
向地球的边缘看去 你可以看到稀薄的大气层向太空延伸
And it's always humbling to realize that
当你意识到以下情况时 你会感到很惭愧
every human that's ever lived
每一个曾经生活过的人类
has done so in this thin skin of air that clings to the surface of the earth by gravity.
都是在这层薄薄的空气中完成的 而这层空气在重力的作用下紧贴着地球表面
The blue fades into black as the air gets thinner
随着空气越来越稀薄 蓝色渐渐变成黑色
but then something else appears a thin yellowish layer separate from the lower atmosphere.
但随后出现了其他东西 一个从低层大气中分离出来的淡黄色薄层
And this stands out against the blackness of space.
而这在黑色的太空中显得尤为突出
You might have seen this before and wondered what it is.
你可能以前见过这个 想知道它是什么
This is the sodium layer.
这就是钠层
It's between 80 and 105 kilometers up depending upon atmospheric conditions
它在80至105公里的高度 取决于大气条件
and it's only a few kilometers thick.
而且它只有几公里厚
This is a region of the atmosphere where sodium atoms are being excited
这是大气层中的一个区域 钠原子被激发出来
and emitting light in the familiar yellow color with a wavelength of about 589 nanometers.
并发射出熟悉的黄色光 波长约为589纳米
The sodium comes from meteors burning up in the upper atmosphere.
钠来自于在大气层上部燃烧的流星
As they hit the atmosphere the kinetic energy is converted into thermal energy
当它们撞击大气层时 动能被转化为热能
and this converts their minerals into a plasma
并将其矿物转化为等离子体
which of course we see as a trail of light on the ground as a shooting star which fades rapidly.
当然 我们在地面上看到的是流星的光迹 它迅速消失
But those liberated atoms remain afterwards
但是那些被解放的原子后来仍然存在
and they stay there for a long time
它们在那里停留了很长时间
hanging out in the mesosphere perhaps percolating downwards towards the surface.
悬挂在中间层 也许会向下渗透到表面
So this visible sodium layer is a lot thinner than the distribution of sodium atoms in the atmosphere
所以这个可见的钠层比大气中的钠原子分布要薄得多
because the transition line that we see only comes from neutral atomic sodium.
因为我们看到的过渡线只来自中性原子钠
As we go higher in the atmosphere the sodium atoms are more commonly found as ions
当我们在大气层中的位置越高 钠原子就越多地以离子形式存在
and lower in the atmosphere the atoms are more formal or more commonly found in their molecular state
而在大气层的低处 原子更正式或更普遍地以分子状态出现
and so we see this yellow glowing layer standing out away from the surface of the earth
所以我们看到这个黄色的发光层远离地球的表面
and as it happens this altitude is very close to that of the Karman line
碰巧这个高度非常接近卡曼线的高度
so it's almost like a visual reference for where space begins.
所以它几乎是空间开始的一个视觉参考
Now the meteors are arriving at earth don't just bring in sodium.
现在 到达地球的流星不只是带来了钠
They have many other minerals.
它们还有许多其他矿物
And all of these also get deposited in the atmosphere
而所有这些也都沉积在大气中
and over time scientists have managed to identify
而且随着时间的推移 科学家们已经设法确定
the existence of other similar layers dominated by different elements.
其他由不同元素主导的类似层的存在
We've seen iron potassium and calcium.
我们已经看到铁、钾和钙
But none of these are as strong as the sodium.
但这些都没有钠那么强
Because the sodium is extremely efficient at converting the excitation energy into light that we can see.
因为钠在将激发的能量转化为我们可以看到的光方面非常有效
That's why we have low pressure sodium lights.
这就是为什么我们有低压钠灯
So the sodium layer was first discovered from the ground using spectroscopy back in 1929
因此 钠层是在1929年首次从地面用光谱学发现的
and since then it's been used by scientists as a way to probe atmospheric conditions in the mesosphere
从那时起 科学家们就用它来探测中间层的大气状况
which is actually our region in the atmosphere which is really hard to investigate directly
这实际上是我们在大气层中很难直接调查的区域
since it's too high for balloons and too low for spacecraft.
因为它对气球来说太高 对航天器来说太低
Now from the ground you can use lasers to excite the atomic sodium in that region
现在从地面上 你可以使用激光来激发该区域的原子钠
and then it re-emits the light which you can observe back on the ground
然后它重新发出光 你可以在地面上观察它
and from that you can measure the motion of the atmosphere or the temperature.
从中你可以测量大气的运动或温度
The temperature of the air depends or changes the shape of the emission lines that we see
空气的温度取决于或改变我们看到的发射线的形状
and the doppler shift can of course change the wavelength that we see.
而多普勒位移当然会改变我们看到的波长
There's one facility that i want to talk about that does a science like this.
我想说的是 有一个设施做这样的科学
It's called the Purple Crow Lidar Facility in Ontario, Canada.
它被称为加拿大安大略省的紫乌鸦激光雷达设施
And it's notable because the primary mirror on the collector system is a rotating mercury mirror.
它值得注意的是 收集器系统的主镜是一个旋转的水银镜
That's a mirror that's essentially a 9 feet wide 2.65 meters.
那是一个基本上是9英尺宽2.65米的镜子
It's a tub of mercury and it's rotating at about 10 RPM
它是一盆水银 以大约10转/分钟的速度旋转
which means that it takes up a natural curvature which will focus the light on the detector system.
这意味着它有一个自然的弧度 这将使光线集中在检测器系统上
And the only way they can make this work by the way is
顺便说一下 他们能够使这个工作的唯一方法是
because it's only pointing straight up
因为它只是直接指向上方
if the mirror had to turn then it would no longer be able to work like this.
如果镜子必须转动 那么它将不再能够像这样工作
But one of the coolest things that can be done with this sodium layer is that
但是用这个钠层可以做的最酷的事情之一就是
it can be exploited by telescopes to help them see more detail in the sky than would normally be possible.
它可以被望远镜所利用 以帮助他们看到比通常情况下更多的天空细节
So as you probably know the resolving power of a telescope on the ground
所以 正如你可能知道的 地面上的望远镜的分辨能力
is limited by the turbulence of the atmosphere
受限于大气层的湍流
which refracts the light from astronomical objects
它使来自天文物体的光线发生折射
and it's an effect that we can see with our naked eye.
这是一个我们可以用肉眼看到的效果
It's what makes the stars twinkle in the sky.
这就是使星星在天空中闪烁的原因
So telescopes can have adaptive optics.
因此 望远镜可以有自适应光学系统
This means the mirror is able to flex and change its shape in response to atmospheric distortion.
这意味着镜子能够弯曲并改变其形状以应对大气的扭曲
And so that it can actually undo the atmospheric distortion
这样 它实际上可以消除大气变形
and ultimately produce a much clearer image than would not otherwise be allowed.
并最终产生一个比其他方式不允许的更清晰的图像
But to do this they need to know how the atmosphere is distorting the light
但要做到这一点 他们需要知道大气层是如何扭曲光线的
so they take a reference star which you can assume to be a perfect point source
所以他们采取了一个参考星 你可以假设它是一个完美的点光源
and then you measure that with a real-time camera
然后你用实时摄像机测量它
taking hundreds of frames per second measuring the distortion
每秒拍摄几百帧 测量扭曲情况
and then feeding that back into the optic system
然后将其反馈给光学系统
so that it can undo the refraction.
这样它就可以消除折射了
And it needs to be able to measure the star hundreds of times per second.
它需要能够每秒测量数百次的恒星
The problem then is that the star has to be bright enough
那么问题来了 恒星必须有足够的亮度
so they can take the image fast enough and get enough detail.
以便他们能以足够快的速度拍摄图像并获得足够的细节
And not all astronomical targets will have a bright star close enough to the target
而不是所有的天文目标都有一颗足够接近目标的亮星
so instead the sodium layer can be used to generate an artificial reference star.
所以钠层可以用来产生一个人工参考星
What you do is you have a laser which is tuned to excite the 589 nanometer sodium emission lines
你所做的是你有一个激光器 它被调谐到激发589纳米的钠发射线上
and you fire that up alongside the telescope
然后你在望远镜旁边发射它
and in the sodium layer it's generating light which is it essentially looks like a star.
在钠层中 它产生的光从本质上看就像一颗星
Technically it's a line through the atmosphere if you look at it from the side
从技术上讲 如果你从侧面看 它是一条穿过大气的线
but since the laser is placed next to the telescope
但由于激光器被放置在望远镜的旁边
it appears to be sufficiently point-like to act as a reference star
它看起来足够像一个点 可以作为一个参考星
and deliver image details that would normally be twinkled to death.
并提供通常会被闪烁死的图像细节
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是斯科特-曼利 飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]